hello and welcome
it's June 15 2023 we're in active live
stream 54.2
so welcome to the active Institute
we're a participatory online Institute
that is communicating learning and
practicing applied active inference you
can find us at the links here
this is a recorded and an archived live
stream so please provide feedback so we
can improve our work
all backgrounds and perspectives are
welcome and will follow a video
etiquette for live streams
head over to
activeinference.org to learn more about
participating in live streams and other
projects
all right
we're in live stream 54.2 continuing
with our third discussion on the work
mathematical foundations for a
compositional account of the Bayesian
brain
we're back with Dean Ali and Toby so if
each want to say hello and
anything to begin with otherwise
Ali has some questions ready and we have
some questions that people have
submitted in the meantime as well so
shall we just proceed to the questions
as we have the same people as dot one
great
okay I'm gonna jump into some of the
pre-submitted questions so
would it be correct to call equation 4.2
compositional base theorem which is or
our basis theorem categorically
and we have the um
document ready or anything that you want
to share but what is what does it mean
for Bayes theorem to be categorified and
where is that in the dissertation
yeah okay so that's a nice question
um I would say that um
equation 4.2 is is like um
it's like it's a basic it's like a sort
of it's like it's like a basic
representation of the product law of
probability Theory
um and so I wouldn't say it's
particularly like inherently
compositional it's just something that
it's just like an axiom that is just
like a consequence of the sort of
standard axioms of probability Theory
the thing that makes it a little bit
different from um the way that it's
normally written
um in probability theory is that I've
kind of annotated those P symbols which
represent like the probability of a
certain event
um I've annotated them each with like
um a subscript and that subscript
represents like like where the
probability is coming from like the
probability according to whom well that
that's kind of how you can think of it
and so normally I find like this this
kind of like P notation to be a little
bit confusing
because people often write you know he
of B given a and they also write like P
of like x given y or like P or W comma a
comma Z and so like in each of those
cases like the the sort of content of
the p is kind of different like the A
and the B might be like events of it of
a different kind to X and Y and yeah
they're all like put into this P symbol
whereas in this case I've I've with the
annotations it says like as I say it
says according to according to what and
so here like the little subscript C
represents
what's typically called in um
in like compositional probability Theory
like um a Channel or like a a kernel but
that is like a kind of abstract way of
just saying conditional probability
distribution and so the little c means
it's a conditional probability
distribution from from like x a space X
to y a space Y and here I'm thinking of
like the B as being an event of type Y
and a is being an event of type A of
sorry of Type X and so the PC says it's
the probability of the event
um B of type y given the event at a of
Type X
and so that means that when you like
plug these like these kind of flows of
information together you make sure like
the types match it's kind of like
working with a strongly typed
programming language
so like that type of information is like
the main thing that's different between
this and the standard like
um product rule of probability and it's
from that product rule of probability
theory that you can just write down
Bayes theorem which is the equation 4.3
I would say
the
the the reason why I slightly hesitated
a cool equation 4.3 like a sort of
abstract or categorical version of Bayes
theorem even though it's annotated by
these channels
um it's because you have this like
Division and like that division isn't
something that's
like well defined in all categories in
all Con in all like situations that you
might want to consider like probability
theory for instance like you might have
this
um EFC dot Pi thing and that means the
kind of like y marginal of the joint
distribution or it's otherwise known as
the the push forward of this of the of
the of the distribution Pi through the
channel C like that that thing might
have what's known as measure zero which
means the probability might be zero and
so the division isn't very well defined
and so like that expression doesn't
always make sense
now the thing that does always make
sense on the other hand is that just
product law equation which which tells
you how the two ways you can write down
this joint distribution so if you have a
joint distribution
like on the Space X times y I've written
it there
then you can decompose it into like a
prior on X and a channel from X to Y so
that then if you like put you know the
information from the prior through the
channel you get the marginal on Y and
that's that push forward thing
or you could write the joint
distribution as
um a prior on why and a conditional
distribution from y to X and the thing
is obviously we're talking about the
same joint distribution in both places
so those two decompositions
they're sometimes called disintegrations
those two disintegrations need to be
equal
and that's what that equation is saying
um so that's kind of because it doesn't
have this um division in it and because
base law follows from it and because
it's something you can write down in all
settings it's kind of more fundamental
um but I quite like the kind of string
diagrammatic form of it
um which is something that is wrong it's
not it's not my invention it's I think I
originally saw it in a paper by Bart
Jacobs and um I think his student at the
time can to Cho so in um
let's see uh equation 4.5 so that's
section
4.1.2 on abstract Bayesian inversion so
yeah if you scroll down a little it's on
like page 130
or uh 130 in my version which might be
hopefully around the same place in your
version
um
yeah a little further
oh man no maybe not let me let me let me
get up the version on because I've
realized I've opened the wrong version
um
and meanwhile see it
[Music]
so the the the thing I'm going for here
is the sort of as I say the string
diagrammatic depiction or uh yeah 4.1.2
it's page 120 sorry about that oh good
um
yeah so it it kind of shows you like how
the information flows
um and so this this like makes the two
the two like processes
like quite explicit like so here on the
left the prior of the joint distribution
is pi
and then you take the the sort of
probability the information from PI and
you copy it and you keep one of the
copies and that gives you your X
marginal and then you feed the other one
through the likelihood or the
conditional Channel C and that gives you
the other marginal and so like if you if
you throw away this x information you
get the Y marginal and that's what
marginalization is
and that's why the Y marginal if you
look on the right hand side the prior is
C after Pi you know that's that's the Y
marginal so like that's that's this is
this is like depicting that product law
and then you say you know
you can call something a Bayesian
inversion of C with respect to the prior
Pi if it is something that can go in the
Box
on the right hand side where I've
written C dagger pi and the reason I've
used this dagger symbol is because under
you know certain you know technical
conditions this this Bayesian inversion
thing gives you what's known in
um category Theory as a dagger functor
um and like that's something that like
swaps the direction of amorphism
and so here you've taken the thing that
goes from X to Y and you've stopped it
and it goes from y to X but it depends
on the prior and so everything that's a
little subscript and so for me this
picture is is a kind of
I mean it's kind of equivalent to that
product law equation 4.2
um but I I think it's it's kind of
although it's a kind of new kind of
language I think it's a kind of a more
intuitive one because you can sort of
see how the information flows through
the system
um so that was a bit of a long answer
um but I think that's like I think
that's how I think of it great
okay
next question could be a short one I'm
mostly wondering about how chapter six
will be Rewritten yeah will it be major
and when we promised we didn't write
this question primarily to select the
best policy as to where to direct my
regime of attention like should I wait
to dig deeper into chapter six until the
updated observations arrive is
reflecting deeply uh up until chapter
five where I should focus for now or is
chapter six something that won't change
too much and I can still explore that
next week
so this is a great question and I would
and I'm sorry that it isn't like the the
Rewritten version isn't online yet but
it's really close I promise
um and I am kind of aiming for it to be
done like next week or maybe let's let's
not hold myself Hostage to Fortune so
let's call it the next couple of weeks
but it is a quite uh it's quite a change
in the sense that I've kind of both
it's kind of annoying because it's
simpler but also kind of more structured
and so that means that there's kind of
there were a lot of like Affinity
details that I didn't anticipate
uh needing to deal with that I had to
deal with even though fundamentally
the basic idea is kind of the same
but also Nita and simpler at the same
time
um and and if you I mean I I can go into
some details about the differences if
you'd like or I can just leave it at
that um like why would you rather let's
return to this in the dot three
okay yeah let's do that that's that's a
nice idea um so yeah I would say don't
you know dig too deeply into it because
basically the thing that I've managed to
do away with and sorry for all the
people who've kind of tried to bang
their heads on it already is the kind of
pro-functor like Optics kind of like the
sort of pro functor stuff with those
weird like co-end things
um the kind of
like integral symbols that I was using
to Define contexts for statistical games
um that whole thing
you it turns out you don't actually need
the complexity of that structure and
um the notion of context
is really given
um just by two things it's really just
the prior which we've already talked
about
and also like the observation you take
from the environment
and so before I thought you needed to
consider like not just the observation
but also like the stuff that might go on
in the environment around the
observation that like gives you
correlations
but it turns out actually you don't need
that at least not for the free energy
principle
um and so that that makes things a bit
simpler because you don't need that kind
of weird structure
[Music]
um
but there's like as I say like some
technical stuff which is very annoying
which made it also a little bit
like slightly annoying to write down
um and involve by categories and like
sorry about that but it's actually the
fundamental idea of a statistical game
being like a Bayesian lens which
describes
like the the inference process
um maybe like a parameterized Bayesian
lens that allows you to learn but a
Bayesian lens that like comes with a
loss function
that's still the same idea
um and it turns out that lost functions
like the relative entropy and the free
energy they actually have a really neat
categorical structure so the things I
was calling like free energy games
before or like um relative like basic
inference games those are actually now a
lot even neater still so that's that's
really nice
um
and and the way you get predictive
coding is still as like a functor from
some from these like statistical games
two dynamical systems so like that idea
is still the same
um it's just actually it turned out that
the statistical games themselves there
was actually a lot more nice stuff going
on there than I had realized before
awesome
all right
work on memory evolutive systems to what
extent have you used their work in the
thesis would it be correct to say that
there might exist a functor from that
book to your dissertation or indeed
to any of your citations is there work
someone could do to explore the
connection between the two
to me this is a question of one instance
if a learner or researcher performs
active inference on the interface
between a work and a citation more
generally great question yeah I think
it's a really nice question and actually
I so I I read
um the this work On by Aerosmith
November mesh on
um memory evaluative systems like a few
years ago and I found it very like
abstract and confusing and I was like
yeah this is this is all really nice but
like how does it actually connect to the
brain and how things like brains work
um
but I've I've kind of softened my stance
on it recently and I think actually
there's some really cool stuff
in that work
um some really great ideas about like
hierarchical complex systems and
emergence and like
um even things like neural coding
and and it's kind of I think like
slightly in danger I think of being
forgotten because people see it and
think okay well like how does it
actually make contact with things I know
about now
um things that like actually scientists
use
and so I think it would be great to
explore the connections like in a kind
of more detailed way I don't know
precisely what that would look like
um I I heard a talk actually by Andre uh
um
I think it it I don't know I don't there
may be some on YouTube I I don't I don't
know um this was in uh Consciousness
maths of Consciousness
um like workshop at the end of April
and she explains some of the more recent
stuff they've been doing and it seemed
sounded like actually they
um there is a proof I think that heavy
and learning does actually give you
um
sort of what she calls cat neurons
and so before I've been like okay well
it's a nice story but is it does it
actually
does it actually relate to things like
heavy learning or is it just like an
analogy
um but it sounds like it's actually a
bit more precise than I had thought and
obviously because of the connection
between things like heavy and learning
and predictive coding it sounds like you
know this there should be a way to
relate something like predictive coding
to memory evaluative systems and that
would be really nice because I I you
know sometimes think about this kind of
direction that I'm trying to go with so
but try to think about
um like Nest image active influence
systems like you know you might have a
little region of the brain and all the
cells are doing like active inference
and the circuits do predictive coding
and they make up a brain and brains make
up a you know Society or an organization
and that story of like hierarchical
complex systems is really the story that
um this work is trying to tell as well
just in a different kind of way and so I
think there's some really it's a really
fruitful area
um and I really hope yeah somebody does
dig into it
um because it will be because I think
it's I think it's great work and I think
it's just work that was kind of maybe
ahead of its time so it kind of got left
you know in by the wayside maybe a
little bit but I'm really glad to see
somebody
um ask about it now
cool just one short remark on this and
then all your Dean please it's almost
like when people draw associations like
a line of sight oh well emergence is
like this it's like they're surveying
and can have quite
far Vision but category theory is like
building the high-speed rail where it's
like locked in
and then we can say there really is a
relationship of this exact formal type
between heavy and learning and
predictive coding let's just say some
type so then that can be really relied
on as a as a foundational building block
and it kind of
um
brings those literatures and merges
those streams or at least adjoints the
streams or naturally transforms the
streams or whatever the appropriate
terminology would be but in a really
solid way that's not just like well one
person on a Mountaintop saw that these
two things could be connected it's more
like an engineering project that really
locks it in for everybody
yeah I think so and I I hope you know
some people are incentivized to do that
engineering I I think that would be
great
all right last to the pre-submitted uh
questions
so in the Park Zulo and friston 2022
active inference textbook
the first question in the recipe for
designing an active inference model this
is chapter six is which system
this entails three pieces of data one
the agent's generative model two the
interface sensory data and actions and
three the external environment the
generative process
so how do these relevant big chunks of
Notions
from the recipe for making an active
inference model in the
paradol textbook map to the sections of
what you've done in your dissertation
that's a nice question and it like takes
me on to like a question of like
action and active inference beyond the
approximate inference that I was talking
about in my thesis predominantly maybe
here I could like draw some stuff and so
I don't know how easy that is for you
you can share my screen yep um let's see
how this will work that of that
yeah okay sure
all right can you see my like cursor
thingy yeah
Okay cool so um
so I like to draw this picture and this
is like the little Channel C which does
prediction
and then and it goes like from here and
it goes like outwards
and this
is the inversion the like approximate
inversion and it takes in like a prior
which is comes from like here
and it takes in like an observation so
we could think of this as like
um
this is like high level
belief
and like lower level
and this is like
somehow you get something which gives
you an observation
and then this gives you like
new belief high level
foreign
lens so that's like what the base and
lenses are all about
um and like the thing that I was talking
about in my thesis is
um doing
you know turning this into like a
predictive coding dynamical system
um because you've got like neurons which
do this sort of prediction part and then
neurons let's do this like like
um passing back of error signals to do
this updating part and they have this
kind of like bi-directional form and
that's that's really neat and so like
you can like put in another one here
another one here or you can just start
with your prior which is like something
that I often writer's pie up here and
then this gives you like a new pie at
this point
and so you know this is going always
from like higher level beliefs to lower
level beliefs and down here you might
eventually get to like the lowest level
which is like you know if you're
thinking about visual systems then
this to be like you know the V1 visual
cortex stuff or like the stuff you get
in like the retina
and you get like prediction about
let's say visual signals
but then the world you know so you get
this predicted but then the world comes
back and it actually gives you
like actual
this is predicted
Because the actual signals and then the
brain uses that to update its beliefs up
here and so really like the interface
is
somehow like this
okay
and so this is this is like lens lens
world
and this is like external world
so that's where the like external
environment comes into the picture and
you could think of everything in here as
like
agent
but this doesn't really tell us much
about
um action and it doesn't tell us much
about like interaction
and so there's another kind of story for
that which is kind of similar in many
respects which is
the story that is told at least in
category Theory by what's known as um
categorical systems theory
and there you get pictures like this so
this is like your like world and there
you've got like a
some like system inside the world and
here you've got
another system inside the world
and so people will then draw like things
that are called wiring diagrams to kind
of represent how these things interact
so but let's call this a for a maybe
there's another system over here
and this is B and maybe that's C for a
its environment is like everything
but isn't a it's you know B and C
um
and so maybe like it's connected like
this I don't know
some like weird like wiring thing
um actually maybe that maybe that should
go like round to here and then this goes
like to that I don't know something like
this
so this is this is just what's known as
a wiring diagram it just tells you how
the systems are like tupled together
um and that would be like specifying
like how the information flows across
the mark of blankets of your systems and
so like this would be like the this box
is like the markup blanket of a and then
this like wiring is like the data of the
coupling of the blankets
um and so there's a whole Theory a whole
sort of story in category theory about
how to sort of compose if you've got
like
you know if you you know it has a
composed dynamical systems of this kind
and so you know what what we do is we
like say okay well we we write down like
the type of if we say if we cool
if we write I a to represent like the
interface like the the data of like this
is like X and this is like y or
something like that the types on on the
the kind of shape of the markup blank is
then what systems theory tells us is
that for each like interface we get a
whole category
of systems that you could put in that
box to like animate it to make it like a
living system
and then
you know this is like a closed box at
the moment and so maybe it just
represents like the whole universe which
doesn't have any like external
environment
but you might also have like you know
something like a company
um
so you call it like company X
and that has like you know some agent
which decides what the company does or
some agent here which like get takes in
information from the environment
and so this this this wiring is then
something that gives you
um amorphism from Like A and B and C to
X
and what this like
dynamical like systems theory tells you
is that there's a let's call that W for
wiring is that there's then you get this
functor
from din a and in B and in
C
to in X which tells you then how to wire
all these dynamical systems together to
give you one that fits into this outer
box
and so this is like tells you how to do
all this for
um just dynamical systems but of course
we're kind of interested in like active
inference systems and so here you don't
just have
like some like you know DX by DT thing
to go in here
you've got you know the data role of
prediction and you know plans and goals
and maybe the maybe then something about
how to like you know actually do the
inference like the statistical game
stuff
but really the story is the same and so
if you have you know this these boxes
again
what we can do is if we have a box like
this x to y
is we can think of the like the
an agent as having as a part of it a way
of predicting say x we think of let's
let's go to be something else
I'm sorry let's call the let's call
these
s so this is like the fence data that
goes into the system and then let's call
this a and then this is maybe like the
actions that it takes let's let's now
call this box I don't know B
um oh no I don't like B let's call it y
um
so now let's think okay well part of
what an active inference agent is doing
is that they you know they're predicting
they've got some some like high-level
beliefs of type y
and then they make a prediction about
not just the sort of sentence data but
also about their actions and then you
know the their body like samples from
this belief about how they should act or
you've got these little cells these
little like mechanisms which try to
correct the prediction errors to like
make that those actions into reality and
then maybe that gets like coupled to
some other system which receives those
actions as inputs
and you know you might have another part
here which you know goes in the other
direction
which says okay given my actual sense
data
and you know my actual actions maybe my
body is still learning how to like play
tennis or something like what what are
my new high-level beliefs
and so you can do this whole like story
again of Bayesian lenses
um
and this goes like there and that's you
know and this is now just why why and
then this is like s times a and this is
s times a so you can tell the story and
you can build like hierarchical systems
but now you have like a way of filling
in
each box
and
in principle a way of coupling them
together to give like
you know composite active inference
systems like companies or like you know
colonies or cells or things like that
this isn't a story yet that I've written
down
um but I know it works and I'm in the
process of there slowly write it down
um so the kind of fundamental structures
that are in the thesis are like part of
the story
the thing that's the the main thing
that's missing is kind of like
reorienting
is this like reorienting this picture
so that it's not like
going from you know here from left to
right it's like sort of poking
down
into like the Box
you see what I mean and this is like
this is like the stuff you put in
so this is like your
your lens thing here and you sort of
fill in the box with your lens
um so I think I think that tells
I mean that tells you how like the the
tongues of the thesis gonna fit into the
Standard Act of inference story
um the main job at least as far as I'm
concerned now is to like
fill out the details
um and then start to talk about things
like what happens if like you know we've
got why and you've got Z here like what
if you know they're trying to form part
of an organization but like they
disagree about what to do like how how
does an organization resolve
disagreements like what if you've got
like two signals from your brain to your
muscles that tell you to do different
things like how do you resolve that kind
of that kind of like
you know how do you get like harmonious
active inference systems in some sense
um so I will I'll stop sharing my screen
now and then we can sort of return to
the
um the discussion but that that's like
again my kind of long-winded answer
awesome
um I can share the pictures I see um
thing you said you'd shared something
but I can share some more things
and then go for it and then Ali
no I I just shared something from
about nine years ago that I was doing in
my programming that everything you just
wrote out
was I just wanted to share one part of
it that confirms that
you could you could come from completely
different places and arrive at the same
destination the whole bi-directionality
the whole Paradox um predictive
parabolic yeah this you can bring this
into classrooms and have it make sense
it doesn't doesn't have to be esoteric
or too
too remote I guess yeah I mean that's
great to hear I'm really glad to hear
that
yeah it's really awesome thanks I mean
yeah as I say there's lots lots left to
do uh but I think an important part of
that is like
spreading the word so it's really great
but yeah that process is beginning
um thanks to you guys
um so yeah
that's that's good the rehearse play
reflex cycle actually begins when you
reverse the direction of thought
reading from Dean's email interesting
self-organized yeah
it's all about this whole cat but this
is the thing
sometimes the the like I love the
questions that we've had so far and I
want to hear Ali's questions
and then I want to be able to take it
and have people not be intimidated by it
because you can really find yourself
doing these things on a daily basis you
just don't necessarily identify them
the way that we are but that doesn't
mean that we
have somehow lost access to the things
that we're discussing today so that's
I'll just leave it at that for now
cool all right
um
in the rest of the time that we have
with you for the dot two Toby
um Ali
uh okay thank you
you can just turn it off
yeah go for it thank you
all right
in base basically Street
to redeem
ridiculous
sorry uh the notion of Mark okay I
notice in your thesis
sorry Ali there's just a lot of a lot of
lines yeah yeah
what would you say is the chapter six
equivalent
is there yet a recipe for Designing the
kind of categorical
um kind of compositional organization
that you alluded to
uh
I can answer that quickly yeah go for a
quick answer and then I think now it's
better Ali yeah
um so the quick answer well it's a quick
answer but it's not a quick thing to do
um but there's a great
book on categorical systems theory in
its kind of great generality
which doesn't
explicitly talk about active inference
like I've been but it does talk about
this kind of
imposing dynamical systems in this
hierarchical way idea
um and that's the book that's currently
being drafted by David Jazz Myers
um I can circulate a link to it
um
m-y-e-r-s
and um
yeah so that that's that sort of spells
out the kind of General structure
um
and I believe
um he and Matteo capucci have got a
paper upcoming
at um the upcoming act conference on
applied category Theory this year
talking about
um using that framework to do kind of
cybernetic like things
um and so what I've been thinking about
lately is trying to fit
um active inference and the stuff I've
been doing into that framework which has
been sort of developing in parallel
um and kind of fortunately and maybe
slightly unsurprisingly they fit very
nicely together
um and so the pictures I was sketching
are kind of a fragment of that other
framework and as I say I think they go
quite well together
awesome okay Ollie go for it
okay sorry about that uh all right so I
notice in your thesis that you don't
rely too much on the notion of markup
blankets uh but instead
um you use this notion of polynomial
functors as it's uh more formal or
perhaps more rigorous replacement
uh with regard to that in your paper
polynomial life uh you say in the
literature and active inference
um sorry
uh and the free energy principle there's
much debate about the concept and role
of Market blankets which are sometimes
conceived to represent the boundary of
an Adaptive system we believe that the
algebra polynomials will help to make
such thinking precise where it departs
from the established usage of markup
blankets and Bayesian networks so would
you care to elaborate a bit on that and
how do you see uh polynomial functors as
overcoming some of the limitations of
the notional markup blanket yeah okay
um so I will preface this by saying I
think some people might disagree with me
but as like I
there is a notion of Mark of blankets
um that for me is nicely defined that
exists in the sort of Bayesian
statistics literature
um and it says if you've got a Bayesian
Network you can consider the nodes in
that Network
and you can ask
um what are their Markov blankets and in
particular you can just Define the
markup blanket of a particular node to
be
um it's parents so
um
um the those nodes that it's
conditionally sort of dependent on
um it's children sort of those nodes
which are conditionally dependent on it
and what are known as it's co-parents so
the other parents of its children
um and that's a very nicely well-defined
notion but it's only nicely and it's
well defined in this context of
um Bayesian Networks
and so it's like so generalizing that to
kind of situations where you've got
interacting dynamical systems
um is something that that like
informally makes total sense you want to
say okay well I have this this thing in
the world and it behaves so it changes
in time
and it's sort of a coherent unity in
some sense and so it has a kind of
boundary
and because it has a boundary like
information and energy
from the environment always have to flow
through this boundary in order to
interact with it
and that sort of boundary notion it
seems is like what is in other contexts
also called the Markov blanket
and I think if you set up your Dynamics
in a particular way you could or your
definition of Bayesian Network in a
particular way
that the two ideas that you know might
coincide but I don't think that's true
in general and I think what people mean
in the literature when they're talking
about markup blankets but in this
dynamical context I think all they
really mean is like boundary or
interface
so the the data of the systems like
capacity for interaction or something
like that the stuff that is on the edge
of the system through which interactions
with its environment are mediated
um and and some that's a general idea is
um something again that appears nicely
in
uh categorical systems theory but in a
very general way and it doesn't require
any of the Notions of
Bayesian statistics and it doesn't
require
um you know conditional dependence or
um
like parents or children of a graph
because you know you might have
something more complicated than a graph
like you might have like edges which are
allowed to connect more than one node
and that gives you a hyper graph and
there of course the notion of Bayesian
of Mark of blanket in the standard sense
this doesn't make sense at all
um but of course the notion of interface
does and there's a certain like there
are certain categories of interfaces and
those wiring diagrams I was drawing
before are an example of a category of
interfaces like they don't have any data
of the systems themselves the category
just tells you how to sort of plug
interfaces together
and so I think it's kind of neater to
think about this connectivity and the
interfaces sort of separately from the
stuff that fills the interfaces like the
data of the dynamical systems or of the
active inference like games that I've
been talking about
um
and so a a really nice kind of category
that you can use to talk about
interfaces
um and indeed to talk about lots of
other things but in particular to talk
about interfaces is this category of
polynomial functions
and it it kind of generalizes these
wiring diagrams that I was drawing
earlier
and it it does so in a particularly
useful way I think which is that
if you think of if you sort of formalize
the interface of a system using
um this polynomial language you can
start to talk about interfaces that
themselves might change depending on the
context
so like when you get into the car to
drive somewhere effectively you've sort
of changed your interface because now
you've got this like power around you
and like you used and it behaves in a
different way than if you're just on
your own
um or if you're like just you know a
normal you know
normally going about your life
um you might you know blink right or you
might close your eyes and that means
that you're no longer receiving visual
signals from the world and so like if
you just say you know you're writing
down your like active inference model
and part of the model is that it
receives visual signals
then
you know talking about situations where
those visual signals go away
it kind of
you you can do it right but it's not
very neat and so it's sort of a account
for interfaces that might change like
this it's nicer to be able to say okay
well
my interface actually is allowed to
depend on that on what I'm doing right
now
um so like you know I'm currently on a
video call and it means I can do certain
things but like I'm currently wired into
the computer so I can't so easily go and
walk around
um like the set of like signals I
receive or actions I might take might
change
and so I think
it's easy to start by saying okay when
we're talking about Markov blankets and
dynamical systems we just mean like
there is some set that is like the
action set and subset which is the sort
of sensory set
that's just it for me it's just not
enough because of the fact that the
world is dynamical you know context
change you know coupling might be
dependent on like you might be in an
organization and there's some executive
who
who's in charge of defining the team
structure
and that means the team structure is
like the wiring of the agents in that
organization but it depends like that
how they behave depends on the decisions
that that executive meets and so like
their marker blankets but like
conditional on those decisions and
that's something you can talk about
nicely in this polynomial language
because you're allowed to have systems
which like affect the wiring of other
systems but it's really not something
that's easy to talk about in this like
standard framework of of of like
um interfaces and boundaries that is
dominant in the active inference
literature and I think that's because
really in the art of Interest literature
there isn't a framework for interfaces
and wiring
um and that framework is supplied by
these categories of interfaces
um and so you can just choose one and
you can you know hope it does you know
you choose one that's appropriate for
your situation that you're trying to
model
um but it helps to actually have one
that allows you to do this wiring
um and that's something that using
category Theory allows you to do because
it's all about composition
awesome
the textbooks will be Rewritten Dean
quick thing Toby does the timing of the
choice in you in your experience
really matter
the timing in what respects just
whenever whenever you do decide to make
a choice
doesn't the doesn't the effect of the
timing the Oneness of activating that
choice
play a huge part in What what follows in
terms of the category yeah so I do you
mean like if you're choosing to use a
particular kind of interface language
say
or describe a thing using a with a
particular interface or like particular
kind of boundary
yeah so I I agree and that's why I kind
of tend to work quite abstractly so
rather than saying I'm working with a
particular kind of interface language
I'm just saying I will assume my
interface language allows me to do these
certain things
and so that's not so useful for like
actually implementing a particular model
but if you're trying to think about like
systems in general it's helpful to work
like agnostically in that way
and so the reason I sort of advocate
like this for polynomial functors is I
think that they are
they sort of
sit in a nice sort of intermediate level
of abstraction it's not it's not the
same okay well there is a collection of
interfaces and some collection of wiring
them together because that doesn't tell
you like actually how that works
um so it does it is slightly opinionated
it's different from certain choices that
people in other bits of Applied category
Theory make
um but it does generalize this simple
case where you have just a single set of
outputs and a single set of inputs or
single set of actions within a single
set of
um like observation and so I think
because of that it's it's a kind of nice
it's a nice sort of intermediate level I
think it's it's one I've like tried to
work with because I think it's quite you
know natural
um but yeah you can sort of totally work
at a very abstract level and that's what
um David Jazz does with his systems
theory he just he's just like talks
about interfaces in general like they
don't have they might not have you might
not have like actions at all
um
you know it's completely agnostic
awesome Ollie
uh okay thank you so much so my second
question uh is about the relation
between uh your compositional account of
active inference and the recent line of
research uh done in Bayesian mechanics
namely uh the discovery of The Duality
between fep and constraint maximum
entropy principle so
um as discovered primarily through the
work of Dalton's active adebel uh in the
last couple of years uh there's this uh
nice Duality between uh The Observer
dependent uh the uh I mean uh the
Viewpoint from the inside Observer of
the agent and the outside Observer So
based uh respectively uh the perspective
of fep as opposed to a constrained
maximum entropy principle but uh Dalton
has demonstrated that actually those two
perspectives can be unified through
showing the equivalence between the
Bayesian optimality and James optimality
so uh Bayesian optimality from Bayesian
optimality we can obtain fep and from
Jane's optimality we can
um we can acquire a cmap so given that
uh the notion of Bayesian lens also
comprise both uh Bayesian Bayesian
inference and its inverse process uh do
you think as it uh the Bayesian lens as
providing a kind of
um I don't know a tool to account for
showing this kind of Duality between fpp
and constraint maximum entropy principle
I think the answer is probably yes but I
think this is a really great question
because I genuinely I don't know the
story here like I mean I I know
um a bit about Dalton's work and I think
it's wonderful
um but I really don't know yet how it
connects to the stuff I've been doing
and it's it's really like an open
question for me
um but there are some like tantalizing
signs that as I say I think the answer
to your question is yes there is that
kind of unification of the two kinds of
story
um
and some of the ingredients of that
story are kind of floating around out
there so I know that there seems to be a
connection or like I know there is a
connection between quantities like
um the relative entropy and like uh sort
of information like energetic Concepts
you get in physics and through that you
can make a link to the kinds of things
that Dalton has been doing with Gauge
Theory and I I feel like there
there is a kind of geometrical structure
that you can put on top of these
statistical games that I've been working
with because remember they are these
lenses with these loss functions and
these loss functions seem to have this
kind of um
as I say this kind of geometric thing
going on with them
but really like
re like explaining
or like putting met constrained maximum
entropy into statistical games language
um is not something that I've done and
it's something that you know you know
um I've been thinking about doing and
you know I'd be delighted to talk to
people about more
um and so I don't know precisely the
details
um there is a kind of other Duality
which I think is quite nice which is
related to this
um and I think
and I think again at the Nexus of these
is this like systems theoretic idea
um
because of course all of this work of
Dalton's lives in this kind of like
dynamical systems world where you have
like dynamical systems like that are
interacting and information flowing
between them
um
and there are some really tantalizing
um connections again of course between
physics and information processing and I
I learned the other day for instance
that there are
certain classes of
um generative adversarial Networks
um the sorry this is just a slight
Township I think you might be interested
to know certain classes of generative
adversarial Networks that you can you
can set them up and the two like
um the two like parts of the network
tend to like instead of settling into
like an equilibrium they seem to like
exhibit some like orbits around each
other so they don't like achieve some
like equilibrium state in the game
they're playing they kind of just like
pop around
um
but somebody was telling me about
like if you have an orbit you could sort
of and you're a physicist you think okay
well like what what is that orbit like
like conserving is there like a quantity
that it's conserving
and in this case and I don't know the
details but in this case
um this person found that the quantity
that was conserved in this orbit was the
relative entropy and so like there's
this weird thing going on look these
things are playing a game but they're
still like at this kind of
like somewhere like steady state or
relative entropy
um and so there seems to be this deep
connection between these kinds of like
game-like systems
and like sort of information physics in
some sense
um and I'm aware I need to head off at a
moment but I just want to draw one more
picture and I'm sorry you probably had
loads of questions but we kind of run
out of that was perfect many of them but
hopefully we'll we'll get to the rest of
them soon
um but if I just draw as I say one more
um
picture
um which is a kind of slightly uh
different kind of Duality but a similar
kind of similar kind of flavor
so what we have in
systems theory is this category you have
in this category of interfaces and of
systems and the morphisms tell you how
to like wire these systems together
to give like hierarchical or like
composite systems
and you can
if you have if you have something like
this thing which I wrote before din
which I said you know for each interface
I was like a a category
then you can sort of think of this as a
functor from int to like cat
the category of categories
and one thing you can do with index
categories of this kind is you can sort
of turn them into what are called like
vibrations using what's known as The
Groton deconstruction and if you know
about physics you've probably heard of a
concept called a fiber bundle
um which is just like a collection of
Spaces indexed by points of another
space
and so what you can do is you can write
this vibration which says okay well for
each interface I've got a category of
inter of systems on that interface and
they're all like glued together
correspondingly with the the wirings of
your interface category
and so you write this as like another
functor which kind of forgets about the
dynamical systems and just Returns the
interface again
and so you have this vibration thing
here
and this is like where kind of like
physics lives
and so what I've been trying to tell
this story about you know in this story
about active inference is that you have
a similar one where you have
um for each type of interface the
category of agents that might be that
might have that interface like you know
we're all humans and so we're all like
the type that might fit in like a
human-shaped box
um and so we're all in that like
particular category and you know we come
together to form organizations and
that's another object of this category
of interfaces and another kind of agent
category on those interfaces and so that
gives you another one of these
vibrations and the thing that something
like predictive coding tells you is it
says okay well given a certain
story about
a type of agent
can I turn that into a dynamical system
which like actually animates it and so
that's like a function like okay for
like this
so maybe maybe what we could do is we
could think of this as like maybe like
some version of biology
or we could think of this as like you
know we could think of this as like body
and we could sort of think of this as
like mind
and so like this is telling us how to go
from like a description of like a mental
system to like a sort of embodied system
and I think some of what the free energy
principle is trying to say is that you
know for certain kinds of system there's
a way to turn your description of a
dynamical system into something that
looks like an agent
and so the thing I'm wondering is that
whether there's like some like
a junction or maybe maybe this is like I
don't know
I don't know which way we might write
labels on these but maybe there's like
some a junction here
um that allows us to like compare these
two processes of like you know turning a
sort of mental system into a physical
one and then going in the other
direction from a physical system into a
mental one
um and so maybe this is also like where
like you know information comes in
um and it's a kind of similar story in
in category Theory
um where there's a sort of Duality
between geometry and logic
um that you that sort of sometimes
written like this you have like truth
values down here and you have like
logic over here and you have like space
over here
and like there's a way to sort of like
draw a picture like this
that says okay well
logic is somehow like dual to space in
some like sort of number jumbo-y way I
mean again I've run out of time but I
think there's a story that people try to
tell about like science in this kind of
abstract world and I think it's a
similar story to maybe something that's
being told over here
um again lots of details and I don't
know precisely the connection with
Dalton's work but I think it's kind of
pointy in this kind of Direction
Thank You Toby after thank you you have
revised and preceded
um
let's have 54.3 and talk more about
action active inference so thank you
yeah great thank you so much for having
me and I look forward to speaking again
and answering your questions about it
thank you so much maybe that was great
okay great bye guys
bye
well
wow
Ollie please make a remark and then I
have a question sorry yeah uh you know
uh I really think of Toby's work as uh
really provocative as it's uh as it
really opens up Pandora's box with many
many uh different fertile questions so
uh I'm I'm a firm believer of this old
saying that a sign of a great book is
not how many answers it provides but
actually how many questions it gives
rise to so uh I really wanted to
congratulate Toby and writing such a
uh I mean
it it looks as if uh he he he began uh
from the perspective of trying to
address uh some of the uh I don't know
some long-held questions but uh then it
turned out to be much more deeper than
that in terms of uh actually giving rise
to many fertile questions so uh yeah
that's really great
Dean
I I'd like to ask what is the difference
or how can we think about being on time
in time and out of time
because Toby said he was out of time
with the answer
and I I know that we've
spoken about this where we consider some
of the time Consciousness and category
Theory work previously
so what is it to be out of time
yeah that's a that's a great question
all I can say at this point is that
it's easier to discretize
when you're in time
and out of time as a as a comparator
than it is to say when you're on time
versus those first two positions
that's all I can say about that for now
because I'm sure Toby from a from a
diagrammatic perspective
could probably tell us what is happening
when he's actually using his stylus
versus not
right like with the result of that
leaves something in and out
but well he's actually on
on point
he he's literally in a different place
so
here's a here's a here's an interesting
thing back to the provocative
Ali and the dot one was talking about
virtual and actual models and was
probably saying it in a in a way that's
completely different than how I
use those those same I believe those
same two models are in effect
and so
um
if you if you for example
draw up
a play say in sports because we're we're
talking a lot of strategy well Toby was
on today and a lot of gaming gaming
Theory and stuff you draw up a play
then you confirm that you have all the
elements of resources that you need in
order to be able to carry that out
and then you're you're as a group
communicating with one another like we
are doing on this on this live stream
right like you're literally calling out
to play in in North American football
you'd huddle up
I literally call out a sequence of code
and then you'd have to literally
reverse that and turn the inference
as as a the shortest
time window into a prediction
like you would literally line up
and then you would carry out this the
simulation in actual terms
this all of that
together
means that I believe that the virtual
version of the model
is as Toby was saying in the
bi-directional sense going in One
Direction
and the actual model is going in
180 degrees the opposite direction and
that when he mentioned
the dagger symbol today I was just like
okay where does that fit in to this
bi-directionality and the difference
between
the the Sim the digital the virtual and
the actual so these are the things that
literally
pop up
at at any given moment aren't
necessarily part of what you consider to
be
the space that is inhabited by
virtuality and actuality and yet there
it is it just appears and then you have
to sit down and figure out well where
does that categorically fit
so again don't want to go off on a on a
deep Rabbit Hole philosophical take on
this but I just find that at any given
moment
there is again so much math in this
philosophy that it's it's kind of
Staggering and just to be able to have
somebody who can explain that and draw
it out
is pretty impressive so
I don't know if it's provocative what I
just said I hope it isn't because man I
did this work for almost a decade and
it seemed like young people weren't
scared by it maybe older folks are but I
don't know
uh so if I may add a brief comment on
just what you said uh I was recently
watching this talk by John Bays about
the history of Applied category Theory
uh so he had this nice diagram showing
uh the relationship between the
different areas of knowledge I mean
going from business to pure mathematics
and uh he he claimed that most people in
category Theory or
in those other areas uh consider
category Theory as being on the top of
top of the pyramid as being the purest
of the pure so uh as being even a kind
of uh being at a metal level than even
the pure mathematics but then uh he said
that I believe a category Theory can
actually be seen as kind of permeating
all of these levels so it's not
something that sits on top of uh the uh
the hierarchy it's something that
actually can be seen as influencing and
permeating all the levels so that at
least uh from the from the perspective
of Applied category Theory uh it seems
to be
uh if not self-evident but something
that uh gathers much I mean more
evidence as the research goes by so I'm
really optimistic in the in the research
reaction that applied category theory is
going and hopefully in near future we
can see it uh applied to many many
different areas many many different
unforeseen areas so
yeah
I think I'll just take on to that Ali if
you
if you use an abductive logic lens then
it's simply a question of when did you
enter at what point did you enter
the
abstracted
timeline because if you see it that way
it's not just top down and it's not just
bottom up it's back to my question well
to Toby was
does the whimness of this really really
matter if you want to be able to take it
off the shelf and use it and that of
course his answer was
yeah if you if you want to deal with
idiosyncrasies
you're left with no choice
but actually to acknowledge
that the the the point in the Continuum
where you take this up
but I I think that actually makes it
quite easy
to see it permeating every level
but again it's the it's the abduction
the abductive piece of this back to last
year in in August
right we're coming up on one year since
we talked about how important that is
and yet
here we are
um what
10 and 10 and a half months later and it
and it we're circling back we have
another predictive parabolic on our
heads
a few few comments on that
it's reminding me of
Professor Mike Levin's work on basal
cognition
and the idea that intelligence isn't on
the top of the pyramid either rather
it's something that's distributed
compositionally across levels and
something that exists at all levels and
so we can then still talk about higher
order properties of systems or or
properties of Composites or aggregate
systems
while also
grounding
in the in the
in the foundations
[Music]
um
so yeah and that grounding and anchoring
and stabilizing that's by itself
is not a
is nothing but a feature I think we also
want to be able to though because
there's a lot of talk today about
being able to see this in in the dynamic
in the way that things
dynamically play out
so again we're back to the what's the
minimum two ways that we want to
incorporate this observation both the
stabilized and as searching right if we
can if we can have one eye on each at
all times it does take a bit of
rethinking
um
there is a there is a there is an
enteroceptive piece to this
what we feel from that
is different
so
that brings us to the Sensor Fusion
aspects of the uh dissertation
yeah
7.1.1 Bayesian Sensor Fusion yeah
a situation that is common natural
embodied systems but which is not yet
well treated by current statistical
machine learning methods
also Ali thanks so much for asking the
Markov blankets
question
I think his response
is worthy honestly to to review and
unpack in in the time we have we can
just sort of review a little bit and
think about what other questions we want
to prepare for for DOT two
how would you Ali restate
the
um limitations of the Markov blanket
concept for all the positive things that
we've said in the previous 300 live
streams and and where category Theory
can help address and and and move past
some of that
uh yeah you see uh so this notion
obviously is one of the most uh or I
don't know probably one of the most
controversial Concepts in whole fep
literature because uh it has received a
fair amount of criticism from uh many
various perspectives
but some criticisms
at least as far as I know is they're
they're basically directed toward the
universality of Mark of blanket how
Universal uh
is this notion as uh as it's claims to
be ranging from I don't know inert rocks
to the brains right uh so does it apply
equally for modeling uh inert rocks as
well as uh the most complex system that
we know of in the in the whole universe
namely the brain uh so the response uh
this line of criticism uh got from uh
the researchers in the active inference
area uh again to the best of my
understanding uh is to the uh to the
effect that uh although theoretically it
can be applied to many
um
I mean different systems uh with many
different levels of complexity but then
again uh for simple linear systems such
as I don't know many uh non non-complex
systems uh it it doesn't have anything
interesting to say so uh rather than
being applicable to all of these systems
the relevant questions should be uh if
it I mean they're enough insights we can
gain from applying this notion to many
different situations and
systems so I believe uh
Toby's
um alternative for this problem uh by uh
proposing the polynomial functor uh as a
replacement for markup blanket uh can
cover this line of criticism pretty
nicely it can address this criticism
pretty nicely due to its uh abstractness
and a kind of more rigorous way of
talking about both the universality and
the individuality of each system so uh I
think that's an a nice way to at least a
viable uh I mean answer to this question
that needs a lot more consideration so
that's my take on everything that's part
of it
okay
and I'll I'll give my
um take two
which is
the Markov blanket concept since the
work of pearl in the 1990s is
actually not doing that much
philosophical work in and of itself it
just describes the parents the children
and the co-parents of Any Given node
within a graph so first we're talking
about maps not territories we're not
talking about features of the world
carving nature of the joints necessarily
hashtag Mal Andrews we're talking about
the Bayesian graph and secondly even on
the graph it's not that a node is like
by its Essence an internal state or a
blanket state or an action state if you
use the first blanket rather it's always
in relationship to others so the concept
by itself does very little work however
people have deployed the concept
implicitly and explicitly
to describe interfaces of cybernetic
entities the kinds of entities that it
makes sense to describe as an active
inference agent so we know from the
particular physics and the strange kinds
work the path integrals paper that we
can describe using
the formalism the Rocks the simple
octave systems and the sophisticated
active systems
in order to have an interface concept
that does Justice to on one hand the
relatively inert interfaces
on the other hand potentially
extremely conditional or contextual
interfaces
just having
some uh tagging system
of nodes on a base graph is going to get
extremely messy it's not that it
couldn't be done but just in terms of
actually doing the programming it's
going to be extremely messy
you're going to need to have a lot of
accessory or auxiliary variables that
indicate
what the current interface is at this
time or what it would be if this happens
and all these kinds of conditionalities
would be like a less elegant way
of describing what our category Theory
colleagues have been developing
explicitly with the wiring diagrams and
interfaces so just to kind of conclude
there people draw the Bayesian graphs
and the particular physics
is using a Bayesian graph
however Bayesian graphs don't naturally
have a lot of these properties that were
really
um being conflated with interfaces more
generally
and by using an interface concept as
Toby said at an intermediate level of
abstraction that's slightly opinionated
but also really flexible
that is kind of the right core screening
the right optimal grasp
on the interfaces that we actually want
to talk about
for active inference agents and again
just trying to get down to the firmware
with the Bayesian graph we're going to
get lost in the details and any
accounting system that we develop is
going to be ad hoc and certainly less
principled or powerful than what the
category theorists are developing
what you think of this
if if we're talking about the
relationship in in with the interface
could we
could we see and I'm really asking this
question I don't know I'm I'm
spitballing could we see the mark off
blanket as the more stabilized version
or form of the relationship and see the
poly
no meal version of the of that is the
search version of that relationship what
do you guys think of that
I'm real and I'm really asking guess the
first just listening to both of you talk
here I'm just wondering if I'm having
one of those unitary moments myself or
if or if I'm way out to
probably give a first first thought then
I'll also give a speculative answer
uh yes so uh one thing that comes at
mind is you see sometimes
uh people consider markup blanket as
being a kind of uh static boundary or
interface uh that just separates uh the
agent from its environment but uh
actually what it really is is a kind of
uh providing a really Dynamic uh
interface between those two internal and
external States so uh it's not a static
or stabilized in any way but of course
uh in some situations we treated uh as
if it's a stable or I don't know static
so
um I mean coding Maxwell ramstead every
theory of markup blanket is inherently
perceptual so there isn't any I mean
static uh conception of markup blanket
at all uh but on the other hand well
obviously for the polynomial functor I
mean not even not just polynomial
functor but the whole area category
Theory deals with objects not in their
static sense but rather in their uh in
the meaning they acquire through their
relations through their morphisms and
it's not about
so one of the main differences between
category Theory and the set theory
is exactly I mean hinges and that
distinction between the static Viewpoint
of mathematical or I don't know even
non-mathematical objects and the the
inherently dynamical or relational
identity of the objects as defined in
categories so I believe polynomial
functor functors uh Again by themselves
are
not are I mean inherently and
intrinsically dynamical perceptual and
uh in in the terms of some Continental
philosophers such as Alan Badu uh
they're they acquire existence through
their imminent relations they don't uh
they they don't need any uh I mean
notion of pre-existence as uh some of
the platonic Notions of mathematical
objects and ideas uh so yes in this
sense I think a polynomial functors uh
I'm not sure which one can be seen as I
don't know more dynamic or perceptual
than the other but uh at least to a
degree both of those Concepts can be
seen as sufficiently uh perceptual in my
view
awesome okay I'll just add with a few
other associative comments one is to
blanket something is to dampen and
stabilize it whereas polynomial seems to
invoke like many names polynomos
polytopos so potentially there's a
multiplicity in the polynomial
that is not acknowledged uh so lexically
in the Markov blanket and then a more
formal way to say that would be a Markov
blanket might be like a specific
realization of some little neighborhood
within the polynomial functor so the
polynomial functor is a generalization
of the Markov blanket and so in that
sense it requires more searching
and it is more abstract and it is more
General but when you do stabilize it
down
then
the Markov blanket formalism May
absolutely apply
but it will but wherever the Markov
blanket formalism does apply like let's
just say that we stabilize down to a
computer system and we have an API and
we consider that that's one of our
blanket States
that would also be
seen as an interface of course which is
how people would talk about it and so it
would be a polynomial functor
and so this helps us look back
at the literature
and see as has been done many many times
in fep and other literatures
recent developments enable previous
developments not to be invalidated but
understood as special cases or or
constrained or stabilized cases
and it only makes sense that we would
start
um
well
putting aside what makes sense in active
inference it seems that we are taking
both paths in some cases leading with
the stabilized and generalizing but in
other situations making unstable
generalizations that then
um precipitate stability
inside of them
so more bi-directionality
great well
we will have a
54.3
with the focus more on action are there
any other topics
that you fellows would like to raise or
if anyone in the chat wants to ask a
question please go for it
in our last bit here
let's look back to the table of contents
or Ali please go for it
uh no just I wanted to ask Toby about uh
the relation
um the relationship between
uh his uh Theory or compositional
account of uh statistical uh inference
as opposed to uh the uh the category
theoretical account uh developed about I
don't know more than probably 10 years
ago by people like Bob kirkey and others
uh specifically related to the
distinction between classical and
non-classical uh Bayesian inference that
that's been clearly uh distinguished in
one of the papers from 20
2011 I guess uh so yeah that's one
question I wanted to ask Toby and of
course a subsequent question about the
relation of this uh distinction slash
non-distinction to the accounts of
quantum fep because in Quantum fep
markup blanket
is kind of replace or rather blended
with uh the notion of uh I mean
holographic uh inner screen uh so how
can we
how can we see uh Quantum fpp as
accounting as arising from uh Quantum
bayesianism uh rather than from uh I
don't know pretty predictive uh quantum
theory and the relation between uh those
two Frameworks of Bayesian inference to
to that topic
awesome yes the quantum category Theory
active fep triangle
um and also I think it's it's
um
the the question about reading the
literature
in terms of the interfaces between a
work and the citations I think is
extremely rich it's a it's a really
novel way to perform bibliographic
meta-analysis but also just in our own
learning Journeys
this um
following this category Theory
dictum of knowing a thing by its
relations
understanding the paper within the web
of the past papers which it cites all of
which are past and actual
and then it's future time cone of
possible relationships to things that
haven't happened yet the co-parents
haven't even happened yet necessarily
but that becomes part of the evaluation
of the significance in the moment
and if we could
have the right generative model and
understand how much attention to weight
onto different
things in the moment
that would be like being able to see the
whole time cone
at the right core screening but of
course it's limited in estimates we
can't do that but we have our rules our
heuristics and our approaches that that
address that nonetheless
um
anyone in the chat or Dean what would
you like to explore in 54.3
I'm just gonna
follow the two of you I got I got two
big uh workhorses here I just gotta get
out of the way so I don't get trampled
let's let's look at the the table of
contents
um
here we're just shifting to the um the
coda document the back end that we use
to coordinate a lot of our work
just so that it can all be seen in the
in the video
chapter one is short
chapter two if someone is looking for
another account of like widest category
Theory matter
Toby begins chapter two with three
examples of situations neural circuits
Bayesian networks and computations where
people often just use a kind of
schematic diagram
but it's not necessary or sufficient to
really convey all of the
um richness that we can add on with
category Theory
chapter 3 starts getting into more
detail with string diagrams
and developing towards circuit diagrams
in this rate coding neural setting
a lot more new vocabulary arising along
the way
chapter four which the question the
beginning of this live stream brought a
focus to is on the compositional aspects
of probability
the copy discard structure
is introduced which we saw in the
diagram today that's when the piece of
information is duplicated and then one
of them can be thrown away
Bayesian inversion the dagger
Lady Macbeth stagger
always just
dangling there
then
the growth in geek
Construction
bringing back strong
um recall of Shawna Dobson Chris Fields
math art
and the complexity of the self
foreign
went into dynamical systems
Markov chains
um
uh open and closed dynamical systems
with this polynomial interface concept
it's really built up in a
extremely methodical way
first the dynamical system is kept
within a nutshell
extremely bounded but then it's
progressively opened up and so even
though it's
um going to be a lot of new information
reading the dissertation it's done in a
way that does also clearly build upon
itself
chapter six goes into the Bayesian
lenses
connects to several
more prevalent Concepts in statistics
maximum likelihood estimation
approximate Bayesian inference Auto
encoders
um and connects this to the emerging
concepts of Bayesian lenses and
statistical games
in terms of the approximate inference
doctrines in chapter seven yeah Ali
please
uh no I just wanted to mention uh this
particular chapter is being Rewritten
yet the moment so yeah that's the thank
you absolutely yes as we discussed a
little earlier chapter six is gonna get
simpler
but better but it was tricky but it's
simpler but it's better but it was
tricky
and then chapter seven
closes it out but really opens it up
with the compositional cognitive
cartography sailing the three C's
Society of systems more alliteration
many many connections to
areas of interest for all system
scientists and complexity enthusiasts
so
what a tour de force
and a a journey and it it's going to be
awesome that we'll get to see
some of the next increments in the work
talk more with Toby yes Dean
can I can I just throw this in and it's
it's gonna
indicate how old I am but
a long time ago the first time a needle
dropped on the first Van Halen album
something changed about
everything that we thought about guitar
playing
and if you weren't there in that moment
you you
wouldn't know how everything changed I'm
not sure what category Theory
taken up on a mass scale will do if it
will be the equivalent
moment for all
people who use math
um in in all the different ways that
they use it but I think
that we are at the beginning of
something
that is it is going to change things and
I don't know exactly how it's going to
change things but there will always I
think this will always now
be included as how we try to both figure
things out and out the figures in that
three-dimensional space I mean one of
the things that I thought was
interesting in the dot one was when Toby
said well I work in in 2D space and I'm
now I'm curious about I wonder what that
would look like in in the 3D well we
exist in a 3D space and so the I think
the applicability of it is going off at
any given moment so but I do really
think this is the start of something
um I'm not I'm not sure exactly what
but I don't think it's I don't think
we'll be able to unlearn this I think
it's going to remain influential for a
long time
so
For Those About to categorify We Salute
You
yeah right there we go thank you
you can always make it better
any other thoughts on this otherwise
great
yeah Ali please with any last thoughts
uh no I just wanted to say I'm really
looking forward for the next
installments I hope it happens soon
because uh again I have so many burning
questions I I try to uh I mean Whittle
it down to some uh I don't know not too
much time consuming questions but uh
yeah I'm really interested in
um I'm curious to know uh Toby's answers
to them so thank you so much for
everything for organizing this and
inviting to me
oh absolutely
all right thank you everybody see you in
54.3